[SPEAKER_01]: So, someone asked, says, Ajahn, it's often said that you claim you must wait until you're a stream-enterer in order to meditate.
[SPEAKER_01]: How do... well, I guess, is that true?
[SPEAKER_01]: What... what... what... or is that a misrepresentation?
[SPEAKER_01]: And the second question is, if it is true, how do you suggest one waits until then without getting bored?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well,
[SPEAKER_02]: Do we say you have to wait the stream-entry in order to meditate?
[SPEAKER_02]: What do you mean by meditation?
[SPEAKER_02]: If you mean concentration on your nostrils, watching objects, calming techniques, then that comes neither before nor after stream-entry.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no place for that in the actual practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what meditation do we refer to, then, when we say you gotta be a sotāpanna to meditate rightly?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, it's the things that the siddhas actually describe, like the four satipaṭṭhānas, the jhānas, the reflections on the subha, metta, things that would purify your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, why... but why would I... why can't I just start doing that now?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why do I need to wait for sotāpatti?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, it's not that you need to wait, it's that
[SPEAKER_02]: You need to keep in mind that what you're doing now will be inaccurate.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you don't see your mind clearly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Uh-huh.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is the criteria... Is that sotāpati?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Seeing the mind clearly?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, when you see your mind clearly, why is that important?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, because these contemplations are not...
[SPEAKER_02]: For the sake of doing them, they're for the sake of purifying the mind from greed, aversion and delusion.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you don't see greed, aversion and delusion, because you don't see your mind, then you don't even have the target.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't even see the target where you would be aiming these shots.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why wouldn't you... why wouldn't someone be seeing the mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: What would be preventing them in seeing the mind?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, lack of the gradual training... lack of development in the gradual training.
[SPEAKER_02]: And views that they haven't clarified sufficiently, or abandoned.
[SPEAKER_02]: Wrong views.
[SPEAKER_01]: But obviously, you know, you don't know what you don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how can you abandon the wrong views when you don't know they're wrong?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, yeah, you don't abandon them as...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, how do you abandon them?
[SPEAKER_02]: It's through the training in the precepts and sensory straight.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, through training in certain actions,
[SPEAKER_01]: That curb, and then eventually not give in at all to greed, aversion, delusion, that's how you uncover the mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether you think about seeing the mind or not, it's irrelevant, in a way, really.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, the... like, you have those wrong views as a symptom of the fact that you haven't been training in these things efficiently.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's... that's what the sutra says.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through purification of behavior, you purify the views.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through purification of behavior that purifies the views, you purify the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whether one is thinking and unraveling the views or not, if they're not celibate, withdrawn from sensuality, or at least not lying to themselves about that that's the direction of training that they need to develop and build towards, they're not going to be seeing the mind, doesn't matter how much they theorize about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, so, clarifying the wrong views, to be clear, doesn't mean that kind of, yeah, reflecting on it as a dry kind of subject.
[SPEAKER_02]: It happens through, for example, when you start keeping the precepts, when you start restraining your actions that you were not restraining before, whether you like it or not, these wrong emphases will start coming up.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you might start having
[SPEAKER_02]: The natural response to try to deny things, to try to deal with the objects, withdraw even more than you're already withdrawn celibacy and so on, and you would have to... Overdo it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, you would have to then come face to face with your actual views, whether you like it or not, your views of where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you would be dealing with them and abandoning those views, not by theorizing, but by meeting the challenges that will arise through the sense restraint, through the virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, back on to the original questioner.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, say, there's no place for any calming, concentration, self-hypnotic practice in terms of the actual dhamma and training.
[SPEAKER_01]: You could say that all of those
[SPEAKER_01]: Meditation kind of... meditations, or views about it, or practices, they do kind of, say, are rooted in a certain degree of need, like a... in a type of need, like you need to do something palpable about the practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, meditation often serves that purpose.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, yes, I keep taking the precepts, I can do this, but what do we do, like, eh... directly, in terms of the... And that's how people, like, fall into this palpable sensation, tactile watching, and so on, and convince themselves through their views, as we discussed in our talks.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, say somebody is not doing that, but that palpable need is still there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, they're not sotāpanna, they don't see the mind, they are training in precepts, and that need to do something more acutely about a practice is still there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there something that they could do to fulfill that need?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's just too pressuring, too strong.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if I don't do something that will kind of
[SPEAKER_01]: If I maintain some sort of secondary identity of me as the one who practices, I will just completely drift away and stop even keeping the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: I need some something grounding to to kind of keep me in touch with my idea of what the dhamma practice is, because at this stage that's the only thing I have.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't see the mind, I don't see the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: I have the idea of the practice that
[SPEAKER_01]: Can't be maintained in fuel through the need of doing something about it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there something I can be doing about it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, why not see that as a problem?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's too subtle to see that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That pressure, that compassion is just too subtle to see.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, I... Yeah, it's a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: They said it's a problem, but I... doesn't have gravitas, that thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, are there other things I can actually...
[SPEAKER_01]: When I feel a need to sit down and practice,
[SPEAKER_01]: In a quiet, secluded environment, is this something that Hillside recommends or allows that I can do?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, ask yourself, first of all, make a practice out of reflecting in what ways are you still giving in to greed, aversion and delusion, knowingly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Say it again?
[SPEAKER_01]: Make a practice... Out of reflecting, in what ways are you still giving in?
[SPEAKER_01]: Give me some practical examples.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, say, evening, my day's finished, came back from work, family, no family, doesn't matter, I'm sit... sit quietly in the room, what do I think about?
[SPEAKER_01]: How do I go about that reflection?
[SPEAKER_02]: Did... Is there any practical way?
[SPEAKER_02]: Did in the course of my day,
[SPEAKER_02]: My mind pressured me out of some obsessive kind of compulsion with something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, you did, a number of times.
[SPEAKER_01]: You discovered it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I gave into it.
[SPEAKER_02]: What next?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, contemplate the danger of doing that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Contemplate how the fact that...
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't see the danger of doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If I did, I wouldn't have done it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you have to realize, if you're claiming to be practicing towards this goal of freedom from craving,
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I am.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just, obviously, I'm failing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if that is your goal, then you want to see, well, I shouldn't then be giving into craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you're clearly doing that, but you're not aware of it, because you're not making an effort to see those connections between craving and the actual day-to-day actions that you're doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, do you mean that
[SPEAKER_01]: Say, a person...
[SPEAKER_01]: I sit and reflect and then I see that number of times I gave in to craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you mean that reflecting on that will gradually prevent me from giving in to craving when the pressure comes up?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, by building up the context that...
[SPEAKER_01]: So I can make a practice out of that?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because the problem is these things are not included
[SPEAKER_02]: These acting out of pressures, more subtle pressures than the precept and so on, that's not included in your vision of what needs to be avoided.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you...
[SPEAKER_01]: When those things come up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, practically speaking, at the end of the day, I feel I have a need to sit quietly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, instead of doing the body... calming body scanning or something, saying I should think about my actions throughout the day.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fundamentally, that's what you're saying.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you would find... How many times I acted to this or this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not for some sake of inventory or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: But just bringing them up and leaving them in the mind, so the mind can also see that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And highlighting, like, this is what the training applies, because then, if you're not thinking about it, you will just continue, as you said, clearly, you already don't see it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's not like it's magically going to be uncovered.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're just going to continue in the same direction, not seeing that as a problem, and emphasizing your efforts to a practice towards these other secondary things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it kind of does go hand in hand, usually.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, for people... well, for whom...
[SPEAKER_01]: The main emphasis of the practice is on the contemporary meditation techniques.
[SPEAKER_01]: Virtue, sense restraint, will always be optional, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Secondary or optional.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, they would do it, and many would not be, like, dare to deny it publicly, because obviously suttas are full of talking about it as a requirement.
[SPEAKER_01]: But internally, it's always going to be a relegated, second-place purpose.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it would be taken as like a easy superficial thing that by being a monk, for example, you already did.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you wouldn't realize there's all these layers to it, things of still actions by body, by speech even, that you did, that were coming out of greed, aversion and delusion, and the practice would have been not to do them.
[SPEAKER_02]: So then, your
[SPEAKER_02]: Emphasis of these other things means, like, you're not even seeing this.
[SPEAKER_02]: Otherwise, you wouldn't be spreading out.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, would it be right to say, on the basis of that, that... Say, even if somebody, eh... is trying to keep the precepts, and they are failing, repeatedly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, on one level, they know, they're not obscuring what the direction of the practice is.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, on another level, more often than not, when the...
[SPEAKER_01]: Pressures come up on a day-to-day basis, they have no strength but to give in to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Would it be correct to say that that also kind of could be boiled down to they're not frequently recollecting, even methodically recollecting, setting a time of a day aside to sit down and recollect on the choices and actions you've been making and doing yesterday and day before and today and the ones you're planning.
[SPEAKER_02]: If the pattern... you start to see the pattern automatically, you start getting the motivation to do something about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you say somebody makes the effort and, you know, as I said, sometimes they keep the precepts better, sometimes they fail, they feel bad and so on, but then they make the effort to think about all the actions and choices they made throughout the day, and how many of those were rooted in greed, aversion, obvious compulsion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there
[SPEAKER_01]: What's the next step, in a way?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there something that that contemplation should now kind of lead to?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, so I started doing that, and what's... what now?
[SPEAKER_01]: Do I just do it and leave it, or do I go further with it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, if you... if you're not confident, like, okay, these are the things that I shouldn't have done,
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you are, you are.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's clear, as I said.
[SPEAKER_01]: The direction of what practice is, is clear.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're not, like, trying to justify sensuality and so on and say it's not an obstacle and whatnot.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, but you keep failing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, well, now that you've clarified those things, go about your day knowing where those traps are, because that's how you don't step on them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Reminding yourself of the traps.
[SPEAKER_01]: Reminding yourself of the traps, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, there is really no resolution to that contemplation.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's more like just realigning the state of affairs.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, because the problem is not that you haven't discovered some magical truth.
[SPEAKER_02]: The problem is you yourself keep choosing to act out of creative vision and delusion.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then, you see this, you see the ways that you're doing that, and then your next step is to not do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's already implicit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's more like forgetting
[SPEAKER_01]: Forgetting about not doing it is how you do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, frequently recollecting the purpose of, of, I mustn't forget about this.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the fact that, yeah, if you, like you said, even methodically, you need to remind yourself, this is against the training, this is going to take me away from what I'm trying to develop.
[SPEAKER_01]: Aha, like broader values.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, it's because, it's like, it might seem like, I don't know, redundant or pointless to remind yourself of that, but the thing is, when you went and did those things, you were not clear about that.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think that's exactly probably the case.
[SPEAKER_01]: It does become almost like self-evident.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I already know this.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But see, if you had kept that knowing there, at that time, you wouldn't have done it.
[SPEAKER_02]: If it was strong enough, if it was strong enough, if it was made
[SPEAKER_02]: On a basis, you wouldn't have engaged in those actions to begin with.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you know it on some level, but it's not about knowing it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's about actively having it present in your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like... And you wouldn't have it present in your mind, because you would ignore it and not frequently bring it up.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like you know you are walking in the minefields.
[SPEAKER_02]: But because you're dealing with this and doing that, you eventually forget that there are places that you shouldn't step on.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's because you were just not protecting the context.
[SPEAKER_01]: You start overlooking the specific places where you are stepping on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Although it's still... it's not not true to say, I know about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Somebody told you, you would say, yes, of course, I know.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But in that moment where you get distracted with other things, you're not aware of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, so you're not doing this contemplation for some sort of
[SPEAKER_01]: New knowledge or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's more like stuff that's... Well, there was kind of almost always self-evident.
[SPEAKER_01]: What's good, what's bad, in a sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: But by actually making a point of sitting down and actively thinking about it, that is something that can be done then, even by somebody who doesn't see the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Who still acts out of their duty to do something out of the idea of practice, that would be a right thing to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: That wouldn't be as misguided.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and then, automatically, if you did that properly...
[SPEAKER_02]: It would start becoming apparent how redundant all the other practices would have been.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it wouldn't have ever revealed these things to you and the fact that you'd have abstained from them.
[SPEAKER_02]: You would just hope that that's going to be resolved on its own if I just double down on this.
[SPEAKER_02]: So you would just like...
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like doing some kind of voodoo dance to stop the fire, while on the side you're just throwing fuel at it still.
[SPEAKER_01]: What?
[SPEAKER_01]: You're dancing, choosing to go and stand in the fire and dance there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you become the fuel.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's also how you wouldn't become dependent even on that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's how you hesitated at the beginning, to even say something.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because whatever you would say,
[SPEAKER_00]: ...would fill that space, that would be a barrier between you and that mind, pressuring you to do something, which was the original difficulty.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then your emphasis would start to shift.
[SPEAKER_02]: There are these things that I shouldn't do, rather than, like, I need to keep doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Eventually, that would even come to, I need to contemplate what I've been doing during the day.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and you become aware of that, and Reikunas, that's already a contemplation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you could see how even that misguided need that I, you know, described as kind of almost part of that identity of the one who practices, that's what keeps you in touch with the practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: People start... it's like it's real as such, that you can't... yeah, it's wrong, but you can't just stop it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you were to, as we describe, as the suttas describe, reflect on your actions,
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, not just in passing, not just once, and then, okay, I know it now, but make a point of whether I know it or not, whether it feels clear, whether it feels redundant, I will still do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I will still bring up questions, self-questioning.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why did I do this?
[SPEAKER_01]: How many times?
[SPEAKER_01]: When that compulsion arose, how strong was I?
[SPEAKER_01]: How weak was I?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there a chance for me to not do it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Where I'm at, in terms of being overwhelmed by the mind and stuff, could have prevented some of those compulsions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Did they result on account of my other careless choices?
[SPEAKER_01]: They were not necessarily so compulsive and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thinking about that will actually, more and more, put even that need to do something mechanically, so to speak, will align it better and make it non-mechanic.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's just gonna align it with where your intentions are, and then you recognize, well, this is actually what the practice is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, and a pattern that you will probably start recognizing pretty soon is, you kind of have these actions that feel like, if you would have really questioned yourself, you would know it's rooted in the wrong intention, but you kind of downplay how bad it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: You think, oh, well, yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Think about it later.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll think about it later.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll deal with it later.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right now, I need to do this.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's a top priority.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, you would see, it's because of that, that then, all these other actions become even harder to say no to.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when you think about things later, if then remorse comes up, because you recognize, I could...
[SPEAKER_01]: I could have restrained myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: I didn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: You allow that remorse.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the payment for it, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you will strengthen the value for next time, not to do it.